Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Senatorial Series, 1930-1946, 436 boxes
  - Agricultural Correspondence Subseries, 1930-1946
    The papers for the early 1930s reflect the plight of the farmers and their attempts to survive the Depression. Many farmers describe in detail the effects on the economy and the AAA on their incomes. Material for the late 1930s generally concerns efforts of the farmers to adjust to increasing governmental regulation over production. Other more routine correspondence deals with soil conservation checks and acreage allotments. The papers for the 1940s relate to Federal control over production and prices through the Office of Price Administration (OPA) and to farmers' problems in dealing with OPA. The material is arranged chronologically by day.
    Missing Title
    1932: Agricultural Marketing Act; Federal Farm Board; farm relief.
    1933: Domestic Allotment Plan; Agricultural Credit Corporation; farm extension work; plight of tobacco growers.
    1934: Bankhead Cotton Control Bill; food packaging bills; tobacco production reduction; problems of the poultry industry; crop loans; tax on cotton ginning. Frazier-Lemke Farm Refinance Bill; Flannigan Tobacco Grading Bill; Agricultural Adjustment Act and various amendments; Bankhead Farm Tenant Bill. Refund of processing taxes; Seed Loan Bill; Commodity Exchange Control Bill; plans for compulsory crop control; AAA and various amendments.
    1937: Cotton loan; improvement of highways and railroad grade crossings; tax on plug tobacco; 3.5 % interest rate on Federal Land Bank loans; Forestry Bill; Agricultural Marketing Agreement Act; Farm Tenancy Bill; Farm Security Act; AAA; crop control versus export bounty; proposal to move the Forestry Service from the Dept. of Agriculture to the Department of the Interior, voluntary versus compulsory crop control; tax on garden seed.
    1938: Compulsory crop control; Farm Bill; peanuts; resettlement; problems with allotments; distribution of seeds by county agents in competition with merchants; AAA.
    1939: Crop control; Smith Cotton Bill; restriction on sugar production; Fulmer Net Weight Bill, government distribution of seeds; Bankhead Cotton export subsidy; Agricultural Appropriation Bill; Bailey Farm Marketing Bill; control of tobacco production; flue-cured tobacco marketing crisis; storage rates on cotton; flaxseed competition from Argentina.
    1940: Marketing Bill; tobacco embargo; trade agreement with Great Britain affecting cotton and tobacco; agricultural appropriation cuts; transfer of Forest Service to the Dept. of the Interior; cotton storage rates; foreign competition with American wood pulp; crop control; Net Weight Cotton Bill; food stamp plan: Jones-Wheeler Bill; tobacco storage.
    1941 Marketing Bill; Net Weight Cotton Bill; tobacco exports; importation of Argentine beef; Agricultural Appropriation Bill; Fulmer Bill for the funding of 4-H Clubs and Extension Service; excess wheat production.
    1942: Price controls; sale of government surpluses below parity prices; farm labor shortage and migratory labor camps; Net Weight Cotton Bill; government distribution of seeds; Agricultural Appropriation Bill; peanut prices; tobacco tax; ceiling prices on tobacco; Thomas-Hatch Amendment to the Anti-Inflation Bill, calculating farm labor costs in parity prices; McNary Amendment for a forest fire protection appropriation; government competition with mill operators.
    1943: Farm prices and price controls; farm labor shortage; tobacco grading program; farm wagon shortage; crop control; Pace Bill to include farm labor costs in parity prices; appropriation for the Farm Security Administration; vote on Bankhead Bill after presidential veto; Agricultural Appropriaion Bill; shortage of corn products; ceiling prices on flue-cured tobacco; reduction in importation on Chilean nitrate of soda for fertilizer; dairy industry and OPA regulations; Food Subsidy Bill; milk shortage in Roanoke Rapids, N. C.
    1944: Food Subsidy Bill; farm labor shortage; ceiling prices on strawberries, watermelons and sweet potatoes; tobacco quotas; subsidy for the dairy industry; alfalfa shortage; Bankhead Amendment on cotton textile ceilings; baking industry and OPA regulations; post-war planning for agriculture.
    1945. Ceiling prices and government grading of cotton; funding for the Agricultural Extension Service; sweet potato market; tobacco markets; forestry appropriation; ceiling prices on strawberries, labor from Barbados for emergency work; Pace Bill for parity prices for cotton; Ceiling prices on cotton, tobacco, strawberries, ice cream mix, poultry and dairy industries; Flannagan Tobacco Bill; registration of firearms; rationing or downgrading of flour; shortage of corn products; Flannagan Farm Credit Bill; tobacco exports; farm machinery discounts to distributors; subsidies to the dairy industry.
    1946: Correspondence and copies of bills relate primarily to individual bills for relief, There is some routine correspondence pertaining to administrative details of the Committee on Claims, of which Bailey was chairman, 1935-1938. The material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Agriculture, 1929, Jan.-1931, Aug. 31 (Box 127)
    - Agriculture, 1931, Sept. 1-1932, March 22 (Box 128)
    - Agriculture, 1932, March 23-Dec. 31 (Box 129)
    - Agriculture, 1933, Jan. 1-March 14 (Box 130)
    - Agriculture, 1933, March 15-May 9 (Box 131)
    - Agriculture, 1933, May 10-Nov. 14 (Box 132)
    - Agriculture, 1933, Nov. 15-1934, March 18 (Box 133)
    - Agriculture, 1934, March 19-June 20 (Box 134)
    - Agriculture, 1934, June 21-Nov. 15 (Box 135)
    - Agriculture, 1934, Nov. 16-1935, March 14 (Box 136)
    - Agriculture, 1935, March 15-May 9 (Box 137)
    - Agriculture, 1935, May 10-July 19 (Box 138)
    - Agriculture, 1935, July 20-Oct. 6 (Box 139)
    - Agriculture, 1935, Oct. 7-1936, Feb. 5 (Box 140)
    - Agriculture, 1936, Feb. 6-May 31 (Box 141)
    - Agriculture, 1936, June 1-1937, Feb. 24 (Box 142)
    - Agriculture, 1937, Feb. 25-Oct. 27 (Box 143)
    - Agriculture, 1937, Oct. 28-Dec. 31, undated (Box 144)
    - Agriculture, 1938, Jan. 1-March 24 (Box 145)
    - Agriculture, 1938, March 25-July 24 (Box 146)
    - Agriculture, 1938, July 25-1939, Jan. 29 (Box 147)
    - Agriculture, 1939, Jan. 30-April 19 (Box 148)
    - Agriculture, 1939, April 20-July 13 (Box 149)
    - Agriculture, 1939, July 14-Dec. 31, undated (Box 150)
    - Agriculture, 1940, Jan. 1-April 21 (Box 151)
    - Agriculture, 1940, April 22-1941, Feb. 28 (Box 152)
    - Agriculture, 1941, March 1-Aug. 31 (Box 153)
    - Agriculture, 1941, Sept. 1-1942, March 25 (Box 154)
    - Agriculture, 1942, March 26-June 30 (Box 155)
    - Agriculture, 1942, July 1-Dec. 31, undated (Box 156)
    - Agriculture, 1943, Jan. 1-April 14 (Box 157)
    - Agriculture, 1943, April 15-June 23 (Box 158)
    - Agriculture, 1943, June 24-Nov. 23 (Box 159)
    - Agriculture, 1943, Nov. 24-1944, April 28 (Box 160)
    - Agriculture, 1944, April 29-1945, Feb. 28 (Box 161)
    - Agriculture, 1945, March 1-1946, Jan. 27 (Box 162)
    - Agriculture, 1946, Jan. 28-May 24 (Box 163)
    - Agriculture, 1946, May 25-Dec., undated (Box 164)
  - Claims Subseries, 1930-1946
    Correspondence and copies of bills relate primarily to individual bills for relief. There is some routine correspondence pertaining to administrative details of the Committee on Claims, of which Bailey was chairman, 1935-1938. the material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Claims, 1931-1939 (Box 165)
    - Claims, 1940-1946, undated (Box 166)
  - Business and Industry Subseries, 1930-1946 (Box 167-173)
    The correspondence, telegrams, notes for speeches, and printed materials deal mainly with the problems faced by the business community during the Depression and World War II. During the thirties notable topics of discussion are: the National Industrial Recovery Act and the NAA codes, government competition with private enterprise, and the Roosevelt or business depression of 1937-1938. Bailey was particularly outspoken during 1937-1938 on governmental policy and attitudes toward business, and there is considerable constituent mail related to his views. The majority of correspondents are textile and furniture executives. Many of these industrialists go into great detail about the Depression, the NRA codes, and Roosevelt's policy in general, and the effects of each on business. Material for the 1940s is less abundant. Its focus is on business problems caused by shortages due to the war and on postwar reconversion. Material in this category is arranged chronologically by day.
    1932: Bill to require contractors to name their sub-contractors in bidding; Davis-Kelly Bill.
    1933: Section 7A of National Industrial Recovery Act; NRA codes, and business complaints.
    1934: NRA codes; government plans to build a furniture factory in West Virginia in competition with North Carolina furniture manufacturers.
    1935: NRA codes; competition from chain stores.
    1937: Business depression; Bailey speeches urging the government to encourage private enterprise (November and December); Bailey's Declaration of Principles.
    1938: Constituent mail on Bailey's speeches, The Only Way to Real Recovery and American Enterprise and American Government; business depression; Neely Block Booking Bill (Motion Picture Industry); Patman anti-chain store bill.
    1940: Neely Block Booking Bill.
    1941: Report on Asheville and Western North Carolina as good area for industrial location.
    1942-1943: Business problems due to war shortages.
    1944: Postwar reconversion.
    1945: Postwar reconversion (inc. pamphlet Victory for Freedom.)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1930-1934, May (Box 167)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1934, June-1936 (Box 168)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1936-1937 (Box 169)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1938, Jan. (Box 170)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1938, Feb.-Sept. (Box 171)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1938, Oct.-1943, July (Box 172)
    - Commerce: Business & Industry, 1943, Aug.-1946, undated (Box 173)
  - Railroads Subseries, 1930-1946 (Box 173-177)
    The material in this section, mainly correspondence and telegrams, reflects the problems faced by railroads and railroad employees in the 1930s and 1940s. Federal regulation and government ownership of railroads and labor problems' such as unemployment, wages, and retirement are the major topics covered, The bulk of the material on freight rates and discrimination against southern railroads is found in the Trade and Commerce section. The material is arranged chronologically by month.
    1932: Proposed committee to investigate railroad conditions; Railroad Pension Bill.
    1933: Fort Benning Railroad (expenses cut from War Department Appropriation Bill); Emergency Railway Transportation Act.
    1934: Labor problems, e.g. wages, retirement, unemployment.
    1935: Government ownership of railroads; Railroad Retirement Act; extension of Emergency Railway Transportation Act. Railroad Pension Bill; Wheeler-Crosser Bill to prevent reduction in railroad employment.
    1937: Discontinuance of Postal Mail Service by train; Train Limit Bill.
    1938: Railroad Retirement Act; Train Limit Bill; wages of railroad employees; Wheeler-Truman Bill providing relief to railroads and eliminate competition from motor carriers.
    1940: Vote to override presidential veto of Truman-Hobbs Bill; bill requiring conductors on Pullman cars on overnight trains.
    1941: Railroad Retirement Act,
    1942: Hobbs Bil l to amend Anti-Racketeering Bill of 1934.
    1943: Hobbs Bill; wage increases for railroad employees.
    1944: Railroad Retirement Act; Land Grant Bill; Hobbs Bill, Railroad Retirement Act; Hobbs Bill.
    - Commerce: Railroads, 1930-1934 (Box 173)
    - Commerce: Railroads, 1935-1937, May (Box 174)
    - Commerce: Railroads, 1937, June-1939, May (Box 175)
    - Commerce: Railroads, 1939, June-1944, Dec. (Box 176)
    - Commerce: Railroads, 1944-1946; undated (Box 177)
  - Trade and Commerce Subseries, 1930-1946 (Box 177-216)
    Correspondence, telegrams, notes drafts and copies of speeches, statements, copies of bills, and printed material relate to trade and commerce as well as to the concerns of the Commerce Committee, of which Bailey was a member, 1931-1946, and chairman, 1939-1946. Information on foreign trade agreements is found in this section, while papers on specific tariffs are located in the Tax and Tariff category, material relating to commerce, particularly the regulation of commerce, the Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC), and the Federal Trade Commission (FTC). Correspondence concerns various bills to regulate the transportation of goods by rail, by motor carriers, and by waterway. Scattered throughout the section is correspondence pertaining to discrimination against the South in the matter of freight rates. There is also some information on the Merchant Marine, although the bulk of this material is located in the Navy and Marines category.
    Affairs of the Federal Power Commission (FPC) and the development and regulation of public utilities are also covered in this section. In the early 1930s an important issue for Bailey and other North Carolinians was the appointment of Hoovercrat Frank McNinch to head the EPC and his reappointment by Roosevelt. The principal bill relating to utilities was the Rayburn-Wheeler Utility Act, 1935. Correspondence and other material related to this act are in separate folders located at the end of the papers for 1935. Material concerning the development of electricity through the Rural Electrification Authority is located in separate folders at the end of the Trade and Commerce section.
    The development and improvement of the nation's waterways is a major concern. Various projects to develop navigation and power in the St. Lawrence Seaway-Great Lakes region, the proposed Florida Cross-State Ship Canal, and Panama Canal tolls are covered in this section. Considerable correspondence relates to various bills concerning rivers and harbors as well as to specific North Carolina projects to develop or improve harbors, ports, and rivers across the state. There is also material dealing with various flood control bills.
    Aviation and its development was an important concern of Bailey's. There is information dealing with the construction of airports, especially in North Carolina; the regulation of air travel; private flying; and the Civil Aeronautics Authority (CAA) (later, the Civil Aeronautics Board). In 1944, Bailey attended the International Civil Aviation Conference in Chicago. Correspondence, memorabilia, and printed material concerning this conference are located at the end of material for 1944.
    As a result of Bailey's efforts, a special subcommittee was formed in the Senate in 1935 to investigate the causes of the Depression. Bailey chaired the committee. Material concerning the work of the committee is in separate folders at the end of the material for 1935.
    Other material found in this section relates to Federal funds for the improvement of highways, the Federal Communications Commission and the regulation of radio broadcast frequencies, Bailey's duties as chairman of the Commerce Committee, and the controversy over the confirmation of Henry A Wallace as Secretary of Commerce, 1945.
    Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    1930: Radio channel for labor; appointment of Frank McNinch to head the FPC.
    1931: McNinch appointment; railroad freight rates; Smith's Creek Dredging Project.
    1932: Bill to increase powers of the ICC under which it could regulate truck and bus traffic in competition with rail carriers; Federal Aid Highway Appropriation Bill; Shipping Bill to regulate shipping rates and operations of the common carriers on the inter-coastal waterways; Davis-Kelly Coal Bill; Smith's Creek Dredging Project. St. Lawrence Seaway Canal Treaty; Morehead City Port Terminal; Georgia-Florida Ship Barge Canal; pamphlet - Study in Transportation and the Coming Partnership between Rails and Trucks.
    1934: Inland Waterway; St. Lawrence Seaway Treaty; improvement of the New River from the Inland Waterway to Jacksonville, N. C.; McNinch appointment; Pettengill Bill relating to the long-short haul clause of the Interstate Commerce Act; Morehead City Port Terminal; freight rate discrimination against the South.
    1935: Eastman Bill to regulate water transportation; Wheeler-Huddleston Bill to regulate motor carriers; McNinch appointment; Morehead City Port Terminal; Florida Cross-State Canal; Shipping Bill; Tar River improvement; Rayburn-Wheeler Utility Act (in separate folders at end of 1935); Guffy Bituminous Coal Act (in separate folders at end of 1935); sub-committee to investigate the causes of the Depression (in separate folders at end of 1935).
    1936: Florida Cross-State Canal; Ship Subsidy Bill; Copeland-Guffy Compromise Shipping Bill; Pettengill Bill; Guffy Bituminous Coal Bill; Morehead City Port Terminal; Drum Inlet improvement; Flood Control Bill; Panama Canal Tolls Bill. Florida Cross-State Canal Bill; Guffy Coal Bill; Casey Coal Bill; Pettengill Bill; Connally Hot Oil Act; Federal Aid to Highways Appropriation Cut; Tydings Fair Trade Act; McCarran-Lea Bill for the regulation of air transportation; Panama Canal Tolls Bill; Tar River improvement project; business depression of 1937. Pettengill Bill; McCarran Air Transportation Bill; Griswold Bill requiring contractors submitting bids on government jobs to list names of sub-contractors; Borah-O'Mahany Licensing Bill; Morehead City Harbor improvement; Tuckertown Dam power project; government owned barge line on the Cape Fear River in competition with private railroad companies; tax on nepheline to protect the feldspar industry; proposal by Bailey for the Commerce Committee to conduct a price inquiry.
    1939: Bailey Travel Bill; Clark Anti-Pollution Bill; Transportation Bill extending the powers or the ICC to regulate all forms of transportation; freight rates; Neely Block Booking Bill; Rivers and Harbors Bill; the Civil Aeronautics Authority; appointment of Harry Hopkins as Secretary of Commerce; appointment of Thomas R. Amlie as chairman of the ICC.
    1940: Wheeler-Lea Transportation Regulation Bill; Reciprocal Trade Agreements; Sugar Bill; Rivers and Harbors Bill; CAA; development of airports, especially the Asheville-Hendersonville Airport;; Pan-American Airways; the exportation of scrap iron from the United States, question on the 1940 census concerning income for 1939.
    1941: Florida Ship Canal; St. Lawrence-Great Lakes Navigation and Power Project; Rivers and Harbors Bill; Flood Control Bill; Federal Road Aid Act to improve the defense highway system; price-fixing bill; bill to regulate freight forwarders; CAA; improvements at the Greenville and Lumberton airports; restriction on private flying, minority views on the McKellar Amendment providing appropriation for America Export Lines; gas shortage in Wilmington, N. C.
    1942: Florida Ship Canal; Rivers and Harbors Bill, including the St. Lawrence Seaway Treaty; bill to regulate size and weight of motor vehicles engaged in interstate commerce; Office of Defense Transportation orders on conserving trucks and tires; d evelopment of airports; sugar allocation. Reciprocal Trade Agreements; bill to make freight rates uniform; Bailey-Van Nuys Bill concerning the application of anti-trust laws to the insurance business; highway appropriations; development of airports.
    1944: Flood Control Bill; postwar highway development plans; Insurance Bill; cut in sugar quota; development of civil aviation; Yadkin River Dam project; International Civil Aviation Conference (in separate folders at the end of 1944).
    1945: Reciprocal Trade Agreements; allocation of radio frequencies for the use of the medical profession in operating diathermy equipment; development of airports; civil aviation; Bailey bill to aid underdeveloped areas to industrialize; Lea Airport Ald Bill; flood control, especially at Buggs Island and the Roanoke River; sugar shortage; the appointment of Henry A. Wallace as Secretary of Commerce (in separate folders at the end of 1945). Airport Bill, extension of the Office of Price Administration; flood control, especially the Yadkin Valley Flood Control Bill; sugar shortage.
    Folders on the Rural Electrification Administration are in separate folders at the end of the section.
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1930, Oct.-1931 (Box 177-216)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1932, Jan.-May (Box 178)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1932, June-1933, Aug. (Box 179)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1933, Sept.-1934, April (Box 180)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1934, May-1935, Feb. (Box 181)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1935, March-June (Box 182)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1935, July-Dec., undated (Box 183)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce: Subcommittee on the causes of the Depression, 1935, Jan.-April (Box 183)
    - Commerce: Subcommittee on the causes of the Depression, 1935, May-Aug (Box 184)
    - Commerce: Guffey Coal Bill, 1935, Feb.-Sept. (Box 184)
    - Commerce: Rayburn-Wheeler Public Utilities Act, 1935, Feb.-March (Box 184)
    - Commerce: Rayburn-Wheeler Public Utilities Act, 1935, March (Box 185)
    - Commerce: Rayburn-Wheeler Public Utilities Act, 1935, March (Box 186)
    - Commerce: 1935, April-May (Box 187)
    - Commerce: 1935, May (Box 188)
    - Commerce: 1935, June-July (Box 189)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1936, April (Box 189)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1936, May-Dec. (Box 190)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, Pettengill Bill, 1936, Jan.-June (Box 190)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1937, Jan.-Feb. (Box 190)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1937, Feb.-Nov. (Box 191)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1937, Nov.-1938, Feb. (Box 192)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1938, March-May (Box 193)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1938, May-Dec., undated: Pettengill Bill, 1938, Jan.-March (Box 194)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, Pettengill Bill, 1938, March-Dec. (Box 195)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1939, Jan.-March (Box 195)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1939, March-June (Box 196)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1939, June-Dec. (Box 197)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1940, Jan.-March (Box 198)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1940, March-July (Box 199)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1940, July-1941, Jan. (Box 200)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1941, Feb.-June (Box 201)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1941, June-Oct. (Box 202)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1941, Oct.-1942, March (Box 203)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1942, March-July (Box 204)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1942, Aug.-1943, April (Box 205)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1943, April-Oct. (Box 206)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1943, Oct.-1944, June (Box 207)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1944, June-Nov. (Box 208)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1944, Dec.: International Civil Aviation Conference, 1944, Aug.-1945 (Box 209)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, International Civil Aviation Conference, 1945, Jan.-Feb. (Box 210)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1945, June-Dec. (Box 211)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1945, Dec. Wallace Appointment (Sec. of Commerce), 1945, Jan.-Feb. (Box 212)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, Wallace Appointment (Sec. of Commerce), 1945, Feb.-March; Trade & Commerce, 1946, Jan.-April (Box 213)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1946, April-July (Box 214)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, 1946, July-Dec.: Rural Electrification Authority, 1935-1940, Sept. (Box 215)